Guide to the Organization of Staff Analysts Records WAG.191
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Organization of Staff Analysts Records
1956-2010, (Bulk 1988-2002)
1988-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Organization of Staff Analysts
Croghan, Robert J.
WAG.191
68.25 Linear Feet (69 boxes)
Founded in 1970 by twelve employees of the New York City Department of Personnel as the Committee of Personnel Examiners, the Organization of Staff Analysts (OSA) became the official collective bargaining agent for Analysts in the Board of Education in 1985. OSA is a member of, and bargains collectively through, the Municipal Labor Committee. It represents employees of the City of New York in the Analyst title series serving in more than fifty city agencies. The collection includes minutes, correspondence, election records, bargaining files and contracts, mailings to members, files on individual city agencies, Welfare Fund records, material on the Municipal Labor Committee and the New York City Office of Collective Bargaining, files of the OSA Retirees Club and extensive files from the office of chairperson Robert T. Croghan. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Organization of Staff Analysts (OSA) is one of the largest independent public sector unions. Its history provides insights into municipal politics and the ways that various city administrations have reacted to attempts by civil servants to organize on their own behalf. The OSA records also illustrate the competition among public sector unions for the right to represent this group of city employees; the approaches toward self-organization eventually undertaken by the group; and the internal politics of an organization whose politically aware membership has been constantly subject to the capricious nature of urban politics.
The Organization of Staff Analysts sought to represent employees within the series of "staff analysts,"a category that had been "broad-banded" to include 88 separate titles, including those of Personnel Examiner, Quantitative Analysts, etc. With this action, the entire category became eligible for representation, under the provisions of the New York State Labor Law, or, as it is commonly referred to, the Taylor Law.
In 1970, twelve employees of the New York City Department of Personnel joined together to form the Committee of Personnel Examiners. They had three goals: that each member would help another whenever possible, to achieve permanent status for all members, and finally to achieve collective bargaining rights for all members. The approach was to offer a course to individuals in preparation for the civil service test to be administered for staff analyst positions. Membership dues were a requirement for taking the course. As the Committee expanded to include more job titles it became necessary for the group to find a new name and thus the Organization of Staff Analysts was born. By1978, the OSA had 300 members. Unionization was the next logical step.
The leaders of the organizing effort approached different unions to determine the choice for affiliation. The first union to take the OSA under its wing was the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 237, led by Barry Feinstein. At the same time, the Social Service Employees Union (SSEU), Local 371 of District Council 37 of the American Federation of State County and Municipal Employees initiated an organizing drive. Other unions interested in representing the Staff Analysts included the Accountants, Local 1407 and the Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375, affiliated with DC 37, and Local 1180 of the Communications Workers of America (CWA). Ultimately Teamsters Local 237and the SSEU fought the battle for representation.
The major organizing drive continued between 1978 and 1982. The Teamsters were the only union to offer what the OSA was seeking, that is, a separate chapter identity, one that would preserve the homogeneity of the unit, as well as keeping the leadership intact. During the organizing drive, both Locals 371 and 237 committed full-time organizers to the effort. In 1978, Robert Croghan, who was serving as Local 371's Field Organizer for the Bronx, was given this assignment by his Executive Board. Despite expenditures of considerable amounts of energy and money, no election was called by the city's Office of Collective Bargaining. Determinations within this office were used as a delaying tactic to forestall actual representation. An agreement that would have provided for the various competing unions to accrete some OSA members, thereby providing a partial victory, was unacceptable to the Teamsters because, as a blue-collar union, Local 237 did not have the standing to benefit from such accretion.
In 1982 the SSEU (Local 371) abandoned its organizing campaign. In 1983 the OSA moved out of an office provided by Local 237 and became effectively independent. Robert Croghan was expelled from the OSA, challenged that action through a petition drive, and eventually scored a substantial victory in against incumbent Susan Millgrav in an election for local chairperson. By 1984 the OSA had obtained office space and hired its own organizers. In 1985 it succeeded in becoming the official collective bargaining agent for Analysts in the Board of Education, expanding its membership to 600. Since then, OSA has won collective bargaining rights for previously unorganized New York City employees in all major city agencies, in the Health and Hospitals Corporation (HHC), and in the Transit Authority (TA).
During the Croghan administration the union has scored a number of organizing victories, the most significant being in 1991 when the longest running dispute with the Office of Collective Bargaining was resolved. With its jurisdiction substantially expanded, the union's membership stood at 3,500 by 1992. From the time of the Dinkins administration the union has steadfastly fought lay-offs, defended the rights of provisional employees, offered specialized training courses for prospective employees (some provided via cable tv), and maintained pressure on the city to allow new units of professional staff to become eligible for OSA membership, always supporting its efforts through extensive research into job titles and duties.
Today OSA is a member of, and bargains collectively through, the Municipal Labor Committee, a coalition of unions representing the majority of New York City employees. An elected nine-member Executive Board governs OSA. Also part of the OSA "family" is the Organization of Staff Analysts and Related Titles (OSART), an affiliated professional organization for City employees who are excluded from full membership by Taylor Law provisions but who wish to participate in all service-related aspects of the union other than collective bargaining.
The OSA describes Analysts as individuals who are employed to break complex matters down into their component parts to enable greater understanding. In the broader world, there are psychoanalysts, chemical analysts, financial analysts, and terrorism analysts. In New York City government, OSA members are analysts who are permanent members of agency staffs.
The duties of the typical Analyst may change frequently with the needs of his/her agency. Analysts for the Traffic Department are in the street checking traffic flow. Analysts in Welfare Centers verify work done and design improved systems. Analysts edit agency publications, approve contracts, do audits, write procedures and do staff training. They also design forms, do personnel work, write grant proposals, design computer systems and devise time-keeping systems. They study infectious diseases for the Department of Health, arrest reports for the Police Department, community development for the Department of City Planning, air quality for the Department of Environmental Protection and budget matters for the Financial Information Services Agency.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Constitutions, Bylaws and Minutes, 1956-2005, includes material produced by the OSA and several of its predecessor organizations, notably the Council of Personnel Examiners. For the most part, minutes are of Executive Board meetings and General Membership meetings.
Series II: General Files, 1957-2004, includes administrative lists, contracts and agreements, election materials, documents produced by various city agencies and departments, chairpersons' and staff files, files on civil service exams and other topics of concern to the union, and files relating to the Municipal Labor Committee, the City's Office of Collective Bargaining, the Organization of Staff Analysts and Related Titles (OSART), and the Organization of Staff Analysts Retirees Club (OSARC).
Series III: Agencies, 1970s-2004, includes correspondence, flyers, reports and other documentation produced by or relating to the various city agencies that employ OSA members. Notable among them are the Board of Education, the Transit Authority, the Department of Finance, the Health and Hospitals Corporation, the Human Resources Administration and the Housing Authority.
Series IV: Unprocessed Materials, 1980-2005, includes welfare fund materials, examination materials, contracts etc.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically within each category; Series II and III are arranged alphabetically by name or topic. Series IV is unprocessed.
The files are grouped into four series:
Missing Title
I, Constitutions, Bylaws and Minutes
II, General Files
III, Agencies
IV, Unprocessed Materials
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Croghan, on behalf of the Organization of Staff Analysts, in 2004. The accession number associated with this gift is 2004.031.
Additional donations were made by the Organization of Staff Analysts in 2007 and 2010. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2010.052, 2010.068, 2011.055, and 2012.001.
2 digibeta tapes of interview between Mike Nash and Bob Croghan were found in repository in April of 2014 and added to this collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.027.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Reports.; Collective bargaining |x Government employees |z New York (State) |z New York; New York (N.Y.); Agreements.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Government employee unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Constitutions.; Correspondence.; Civil service |z New York (State) |z New York.; Minutes (administrative records); AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.); Municipal Labor Committee (New York, N.Y.); Organization of Staff Analysts; Croghan, Robert J.; New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; New York (N.Y.). Human Resources Administration; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority; Organization of Staff Analysts; Croghan, Robert J.
- Series I: Constitutions, By-Laws and Minutes.
  - Constitution: Council of Personnel Examiners (COPE), undated, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution: Union of Personnel Examiners [1957?], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (new), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (old), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees Local 154 P, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: Personnel Examiners Council #408, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: Professional Personnel Association, Association of Personnel Examiners Local 188: Municipal Personnel Examiners and Analysts, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: Council of Personnel Examiners (COPE) Executive Board, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, [1980s] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Minutes: Council of Personnel Examiners (COPE) General Membership Meetings, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (video only), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (video only), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General Membership Meetings (mostly on video), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: Joint OSA-AMA Executive Board Meeting, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: OSA-Teamsters Meeting, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series II: General Files
  - Administrative Lists, Jun 1997-Jul 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Lists, Aug 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Lists, Feb 1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Lists, Jul 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Lists, Aug 2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Lists, Sep 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Lists, Nov 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Lists, Feb 2001 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Lists, Mar 2001 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Lists, Apr 2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Lists, May 2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Administrative Lists, May 21, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Administrative Staff Analyst: Promotion Exam Materials, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Staff Analysts: Promotional Lists, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Agency Shop Agreement, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Agency Shop Agreement, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Agency Shop Agreement, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Agency Shop Agreement, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Agency Shop Agreement, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Albanese, Sal for Mayor: Press releases and related materials, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - American Arbitration Association: Grievance Processing-A Skills Training Workshop (loose materials), Jun 13, 1991-Jun 14, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - American Arbitration Association: Grievance Processing-A Skills Training Workshop (manual), Jun 13, 1991-Jun 14, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Financial Standards Code, Jan 29, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): General, 1970s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): International Constitution as Amended at the 29th International Convention, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Judicial Panel Case No. 80-63 Lindenthal, et al. v. Flaherty, et al., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Judicial Panel Case No. 81-9-A Jorge, et al. v. Sperling and McKeon, May 11, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) Local 2021: Audit Report, Jan 1, 1979-Aug 31, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Americans with Disabilities Act: Sign Language Interpreter Services, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Americans with Disabilities Act: Mediation, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Americans with Disabilities Act: Technical Assistance Manual on the Employment Provisions (Title 1) of the Americans with Disabilities Act, Jan 1992 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Analysis Of The Financial And Operating Practices Of Union Administered Benefit Funds: Bureau of Financial Audit Fiscal Year 1987 (City of New York Report of the Controller), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Analysis Of The Financial And Operating Practices Of Union Administered Benefit Funds: Bureau of Financial Audit Fiscal Year 1988 (City of New York Report of the Controller), 1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Analyst Recognition Election, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Analysts Organizing Drive Materials, [1978?] (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Associate Staff Analyst List, undated, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Associate Staff Analyst Litigation, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Associate Staff Analyst Promotional Lists (chart), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Ballot: OSA Contract, 1/92-3/95 Contract, Sep 12, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Ballots: Proposed Citywide Agreement, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Bargaining Demands, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Bargaining Demands: [Croghan copy and notes], 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Bargaining Demands, Jan 1, 1992-Mar 31, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Bargaining Demands [Robert Croghan's copy], Apr 1, 2000-Jan 30, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Blank stationery and forms, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Borough of the Bronx: By-Laws, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Budget Committee Materials, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Building a City-Building a Union: History of the Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375, DC 37, AFSCME, AFL-CIO - 50th Anniversary, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Building a City-Building a Union: History of the Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375, DC 37, AFSCME, AFL-CIO - 60th Anniversary, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Building the Local Union: AFL-CIO Department of Education, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bulk Mailing, Aug 1, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Calendar of the City Planning Commission, Dec 9, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Call Lists: Handwritten, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Campaign for Election, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Campaign for Election, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Campaign for Election, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Campaign for Leadership: Croghan materials, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Campaign for Leadership: Elections, Dec 11, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Campaign for Leadership: Materials re: Electing Union Officers, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Campaign for Leadership: Member Lists, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Campaign for Leadership: Mullgrav materials, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Campaign for Leadership, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - City Agency Listings in Classification Register, Numeric Index, Apr 9, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - City Master File Local 371 by Dept. Dist. Name, Feb 28, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - City of New York Department of Personnel Bureau of Civil Service Administration: Agency Investigation Manual, Jan 25, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - City of New York Department of Personnel Bureau of Civil Service Administration: Personnel Office Guidelines, Jan 25, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - City of New York Payroll System: Union Dues Check-off Roster, Nov 31, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Citywide Agreement: City of New York and District Council 37, AFSCME, AFL-CIO, July 1, 1985-June 30, 1987, including Supplemental Agreement, May 23, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Citywide Agreement: 1990-1992 Sick Leave for Family Illness, Article 5, Section 5 (a) (ii), Jan 3, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Citywide Agreement: Procedure for Paying Supper Money through the Payroll Management System, Nov 14, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Citywide Classifieds, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Citywide Contract: Between the City of New York and District Council 37, Jan 1, 1995-Jun 30, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Citywide Contract for July 1, 1976-June 30, 1978, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Citywide Contracts: Comparison Between Current and Proposed, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Citywide Demands, 1978-1980 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Citywide Managerial Performance Appraisal System (MPAS), 1996 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Citywide Memorandum of Agreement, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Citywide Summary of 1987 Demands, Jul 31, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Election Correspondence, Apr 1995-May 1995 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Election Correspondence, Jun 1995-Jul 1995 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): General, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): General, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Legal briefs for case stemming from 1995 elections, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Materials re: Constitution, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Member Lists, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Member Mailing, Apr 21, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Membership Applications, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Membership Applications, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Civil Service Merit Council (CSMC): Whistleblower Program, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU): Convention Call, May 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Coalition of Unions in Public Education (COUPE): Legislative Breakfast Conference, Mar 14, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Commission on Human Rights: Employee Manual, Jul 1, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Committee to Re-Elect Councilman Rafael Castaneina Colon, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Communication Workers of America (CWA): Cheliotes, Arthur (President) Testimony before the New York City Council Finance Committee, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Community Services and Rehabilitation Counsellors [sic] Handbook (New York Central Labor Council), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)